# Matthias Bachfischer

Munich, Germany

■ bachfischer.matthias@gmail.com | 💣 bachfischer.me | 🖸 Bachfischer | 🛅 Bachfischer

### Summary\_

About to finish my studies in Data Science (M.Sc.) at the University of Melbourne. Prior to my studies, I worked as an IT Architect at BCG Platinion. I have a strong technical background in statistics & machine learning and deep business expertise in digital transformation topics.

#### Skills

**Programming Languages** Proficient in Python, Java and R. Familiar with Go, JavaScript and C / C++

IT Certifications Certified SCRUM Master (PSM I), Certified Product Owner (PSPO I) **Software Frameworks** Various ML frameworks (PyTorch, Tensorflow), Apache Hadoop

#### Education

#### The University of Melbourne

Melbourne, Australia

Mar. 2020 - Mar. 2022 M.Sc. IN DATA SCIENCE

- Learned advanced concepts in the area of statistics, probability and computer science
- Experimented with various frameworks and techniques for machine learning & deep learning
- · Title of final thesis: An Investigation Into the Effectiveness of Learned Indexes under Adversarial Settings

#### Ostbayerische Technische Hochschule Regensburg

Regensburg, Germany

B.Sc. in Business Information Technology

Oct. 2014 - Feb. 2018

- · Learned various programming languages (Java, Javascript etc.), databases, computer networks and operating systems
- Evaluated the feasibility of applying machine learning in intrusion detection systems
- Title of final thesis: Success Factors in Business-Managed IT

#### Universidad de Buenos Aires

Buenos Aires, Argentina

LICENCIATURA EN ANÁLISIS DE SISTEMAS

Mar. 2016 - Jul. 2016

· Completed a semester abroad as an exchange student in the Faculty of Engineering (Facultad de Ingeniería)

#### **Industrie- und Handelskammer Regensburg**

Regensburg, Germany

IT SPECIALIST (SYSTEM INTEGRATION)

Jul. 2013 - Jan. 2017

• Received professional training as part of the integrated degree program at KRONES AG

# Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

**BCG Platinion GmbH** Munich, Germany

IT ARCHITECT & VISITING ASSOCIATE

Jul. 2018 - Mar. 2020

- Advised various companies from Industrial Goods & Automotive sector on digital transformation & IT strategy
- · Designed, built, and implemented digital platforms and IT architectures using state-of-art technologies

#### King Abdullah University of Science and Technology

Thuwal, Saudi-Arabia

Apr. 2018 - Jul. 2018

- · Published a paper on using Machine Learning & Deep Learning techniques to classify toxic comments in online social networks
- Designed and developed a dataset-driven search engine for scientific publications

**KRONES AG** Neutraubling, Germany

INTEGRATED DEGREE PROGRAM - INFORMATION SYSTEMS

Jul. 2013 - Feb. 2018

• Implemented various IoT use cases on a Apache Hadoop Big Data Platform

• Restructured the software- and requirements engineering processes at KRONES

**KRONES do Brasil** São Paulo, Brazil

INTERNSHIP

Aug. 2015 - Sept. 2015

- · Performed the migration of a stand-alone e-mail system to centrally hosted system based on MS Exchange
- · Mentored the local IT staff to carry out IT support activities related to email and mobile device management

## **Projects**

#### Implementation of a real-time data analytics platform for connected cars

 Designed and implemented a cloud-based real-time data analytics platform for a leading German automotive OEM to process and analyze streaming data from connected cars

#### Design of a target IT architecture to enable analytics use cases in manufacturing

· Designed a target IT architecture to enable implementation of manufacturing analytics use cases for a large automotive supplier

#### **Honors & Awards**.

2016 **Scholarship**, German Academic Scholarship Foundation

Bonn, Germany

2020 Study Abroad Scholarship, German Academic Exchange Service

Bonn, Germany

#### **Publications**

#### Success Factors in Business-Managed IT

Berlin, Germany

SKILL - STUDIERENDENKONFERENZ INFORMATIK

Sept. 2018

• Presented a research paper from a case study analysis of critical success factors in Business-Managed IT (i.e. Shadow-IT systems that are operated overtly and with support of the IT organization)

#### Offensive Comment Classification on German Language Microposts

Vienna, Austria

GERMEVAL 2018 - SHARED TASK ON THE IDENTIFICATION OF OFFENSIVE LANGUAGE

Sept. 2018

• Presented the participation of the KAUST Laboratory for Machine Intelligence and kNowledge Engineering (MINE) at the GermEval 2018 shared task (research paper + poster)

# **Academic Experience**

#### Java Programming Lecture - Ostbayerische Technische Hochschule Regensburg

Regensburg, Germany

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Oct. 2017 - Feb. 2018

- Teaching assistant for Java Programming lecture ("Programming 2")
- · Responsible for weekly programming exercises with first-year students

# Languages \_\_\_\_\_

| German, maternal language  | native speaker  |
|----------------------------|-----------------|
| English, excellent command | Level C2 (CEFR) |
| Spanish, very good command | Level C1 (CEFR) |
| Portuguese, good command   | Level B2 (CEFR) |
| Arabic, working knowledge  | Level B1 (CEFR) |
| Chinese, basic knowledge   | Level A1 (CEFR) |

# **Extracurricular Activity**

#### **International Negotiating Skills**

Regensburg, Germany

Additional Training

Oct. 2015 - Jul. 2017

• Lectures and seminars on theoretical frameworks for cross-cultural studies and advice on how to act in an international environment

#### Campus Asyl - Association to support refugees in Germany

Regensburg, Germany

MENTOR

Mar. 2017 - Aug. 2017

· Mentoring and assistance for refugees studying for a university degree at OTH Regensburg